KAIYU YANG: And, hey, it's
great to see you here.
I'm Kaiyu, and I will talk
about Formal Reasoning Meets
LLMs: Towards AI for
Mathematics and Verification.
OK, so we are now kind of in
an arms race of large language
models in which every leading
company releases a new model
in every few months.
So at the center of this
arms race is math and coding.
For example, when
OpenAI introduces o1,
you typically see
this kind of charts
showing that its capability
in various benchmarks.
And you see the math
competition like AIME
and the coding competition
like Codeforces
are usually highlighted.
And similarly, when
Google released Gemini
and when xAI released
Grok, they also
highlight the capability
in math and coding.
And in November '19--
in November 2023, XTX Markets,
which is a British hedge fund,
launched the AI/MO prize.
That's $10 million for AI that
can win a gold medal in IMO.
And not long after
that, in July 2024,
Google DeepMind announced that
AlphaProof and AlphaGeometry
have achieved the
silver medal level.
I guess that's the content
of the last lecture.
And if you want to go beyond
high school competition math,
we have this Epoch AI.
It introduced a benchmark
called FrontierMath,
which includes research level
mathematical questions that's
curated by professional
mathematicians.
And not long after
that, OpenAI o3
announced that it can solve
more than 20% of that.
And which came as a surprise
because when FrontierMath
benchmark was released,
people thought,
OK, this is going to be--
it's going to take a few
years for language models
to make real progress.
But really, after
less than one year,
we have groundbreaking
results from OpenAI.
So why are people interested
in math and coding?
Why are they often highlighted?
One reason is that
math and coding
are proxies for complex
reasoning and planning.
And reasoning and
planning they are not
only important for
human intelligence,
but they are also one
of the major challenges
for current large
language models.
And they can really unlock
unlimited applications
if you can make language
models be able to reason
and be able to plan.
For example, you can have them
do travel planning for you
and also have language
model agent scheduling,
calendar invites for you.
And the second
reason that people
are interested in
math and coding
is they are relatively
easy to evaluate.
Because for a math
problem, you can
check if the answer is correct.
And for coding, you
can run the unit test
to see if they can
pass all the tests.
But if you ask your language
model to write a crime fiction,
or you ask it to
compose a symphony,
it's going to be much,
much harder to evaluate.
You can argue that
crime fiction also
involves reasoning and
composing a symphony definitely
need planning.
So they also need
reasoning and planning,
but they are just not
as easy to evaluate.
So I put it relatively easy here
because as we will come back,
we don't think
checking the answers
or running the unit test
is a perfect evaluation.
We are just arguing that
it's a reasonable evaluation,
and we will revisit
this point later
in the rest of this lecture.
OK, so we know
language models are
racing to be good
at math and coding,
and next we want to briefly
introduce the main techniques
behind them.
How do we train language
models to solve math problems?
Here we focus on math,
but the discussion largely
also applies to coding as well.
And we will see later that math
and coding are deeply connected.
And state of the art
math language models
are trained using
mainly two techniques.
One is supervised
fine tuning or SFT,
and the other is
reinforcement learning or RL.
And we're going to present
a very high level view
and emphasizing the need for
data and for verifiability.
Starting with SFT.
So in SFT, you have
a base model that's
a generic language model
pre-trained on internet scale
data sets.
And to learn mathematics,
you give it additional data
that's focused on mathematics.
So you can grab web
pages from MathOverflow
or you can have
papers from arXiv.
And the result of
this fine tuning
is called the base
math language model.
Well, it has seen a
lot of mathematics,
but it still hasn't yet
learned how to solve problems.
So the next step is to
give it a lot of problems
and with this detailed
step-by-step solutions
for these problems.
And optionally, in the solution,
you can use external tools.
So here the model is
trained to produce
not only natural
language reasoning,
but also it can call
external tools like Python.
So this is an example of
a problem it can solve.
So the most important thing in
this pipeline, as you can see,
is data set.
You need data set for
continuous pre-training.
That's the web documents
collected from web
from the mass forums
like Stack Overflow.
And you also have to annotate
a lot of data for further fine
tuning, consisting of problems
with step-by-step solutions.
And I would say collecting this
data set is one of the most
expensive part in this pipeline,
because it cannot be fully
automated.
You need human to annotate
the data, to clean the data,
and to transform the data into
the data set that you can use.
So what if our data set has
only the final answer, but not
the intermediate steps?
This is a scenario where you
don't want humans to annotate
data very expensively,
but maybe you
can more cheaply get the data
that has only the final answer.
So can we still use this
data set to train the model?
And the answer is yes.
We can use
reinforcement learning
to train the model
to generate solutions
with only the problem
and the final answer.
Here's how it works.
So you have the problem and you
give it to the language model.
And the model
generates a solution
that has intermediate
steps and that
also has the final solution.
And you can check if the final
solution is correct by comparing
it with the ground truth.
So here, it's a
correct solution.
And the model can also
generate incorrect solution
and you can check.
So the result of
this verification
can be used as reward signal
in reinforcement learning,
and you can use
algorithms like GRPO
to optimize the model
to achieve high rewards.
Well, you can treat the reward
for a correct solution to be 1.
And if it's an
incorrect solution,
the reward is going to be 0.
So this approach is very simple
approach and very powerful idea.
It's actually the idea is
there for several decades,
but it was first shown to work
for training reasoning language
models by DeepSeek-R1.
That's fairly recently.
And this idea is getting
a lot of momentum.
Just to see how much
momentum it has.
Just one month ago, two pioneers
in reinforcement learning,
Richard Sutton and Andrew
Barto, won the ACM Turing Award.
So here, in
reinforcement learning,
the key is really
the verifiability.
So you have to be able
to verify the results.
You have to be able to tell if
the solution is correct or not.
Otherwise, you don't
have the reward.
So if the solution has a
final answer, that's a number.
If it has a numerical
solution, you
can always check by comparing
with the ground truth.
But what if it's a
theorem proving problem?
So you are asked to
generate a proof.
But there's really no--
well, no easy way to tell if
the proof is correct or not.
Can we still do
reinforcement learning?
We will revisit this point in
the later part of this talk.
So here we have covered
the main techniques
to train language models for
math, supervised learning
and reinforcement learning.
I would say any state-of-the-art
masked language models is kind
of like it's a combination
of a very strong base model.
And these two techniques
for post-training
and maybe more importantly,
marvelous engineering efforts.
So the algorithms are
very straightforward.
Pretty much every
leading industry lab
is using the same algorithm.
But what really
matters is who has
the better infrastructure,
better engineering,
and better data set.
So then we will ask, will
AI soon solve mathematics
since we have this
very powerful recipe?
And the answer is definitely no.
So we have a few gaps.
So the first gap is how do
we go from pre-college math
to advanced math?
Existing successes are
as we see they are mostly
limited on pre-college
math like IMO or AIME.
And if you give language
models more advanced
mathematical problems,
they still struggle.
So this quote is
from Terry Tao, who
is one of the most prominent
mathematicians nowadays.
And he said, he
played with OpenAI o1.
And he finds they still struggle
with the most advanced research
mathematical tasks.
Well, this is kind of expected
because mathematical research
is by definition novel.
And since it's novel, you
don't have a lot of data
to train language models.
And also, o3 results
on FrontierMath,
as we mentioned before.
They are on advanced
mathematical problems,
but it comes with a few caveats.
Well, the first
caveat is that there
are financial ties between
Epoch AI and OpenAI
that were later disclosed.
But I would say
more importantly,
there's a difference
between FrontierMath
and real mathematical research.
The problems in
FrontierMath are designed
to have numerical solutions,
so they are advanced.
They are very advanced
math, but they are designed
to have a numerical solution.
So this is kind of
counterintuitive
because we know most
problems in advanced math
they don't have
numerical solutions,
but they designed the
benchmark in this way in order
for the models to be evaluated.
And so this is related
to the second gap.
Current models are very good at
guessing the answer, but how do
we get it to write proofs?
And the recent study has
found language models still
struggle in writing
even very basic proofs.
So PutnamBench-- Putnam is
the mathematical competition
for undergrads.
And people recently tried
using OpenAI's reasoning model
on Putnam, and
here's the result.
I'm very unimpressed by ChatGPT
in the recent Putnam exam,
and it can--
most answers are worth one or
two points out of 10 points.
So this is checked by
human mathematician.
And recently, in another
paper, researchers
evaluated language models
proofs for the USAMO exam.
And they showed that all
the models scored around 5%,
so which is pretty low.
And the errors those language
models are making they
can be pretty easy to spot
once you pointed them out.
But if it's in a long proof,
it's very hard to detect them.
So here's an example.
We are asking the model to
prove a very simple inequality.
So if ABC satisfies
some condition
and then there should be
some-- you have some results.
And here it's making an error.
When it tries to multiply
an existing inequality
by a positive number, it
should preserve the direction
of the inequality.
But it flipped the direction,
so that's a very simple error
if you point it out.
So we argue that
current language models,
the current approach for
training language models
is not sufficient for
solving these problems
because it relies heavily on
data and on verifiability.
And when you work with advanced
mathematics, as we said,
you don't have enough data.
The data is very scarce.
And when you work with proofs,
you don't have verifiability.
And in advanced mathematics,
most problems requires proofs.
So if language models are not
enough, what else do we need?
In a recent position paper
we released on arXiv,
we argued that one
important missing
point is formal reasoning.
Here, formal reasoning means
you grant mathematical reasoning
in formal systems.
And formal systems they
can include first order
logic, higher order
logic, dependent type
theory, or even computer
programs and their semantics.
And the role of
formal system here
is to try to verify the proofs
and provide automatic feedback
on the proofs.
So this is very useful because
the feedback it provides
can mitigate data scarcity.
You can have the model learn
from automatic feedback,
and you don't need to collect
as much human created data.
And second, now you
can do verification,
which enable you to evaluate
the model rigorously.
So therefore, we argue
that to move forward we
really need to integrate
formal reasoning
into the current approach.
So we're going to
very briefly introduce
Lean, which is a kind of formal
system we focus on in this talk.
And it's also used
in AlphaProof,
so I guess people already
have some familiarity on Lean.
So here is here's
a programming Lean.
In this program you first
define natural numbers.
So a natural number is
either 0 or a successor
of another natural number.
And then you define addition
between two natural numbers,
so this is just a
recursive function.
And then you can state
and prove some theorems
about natural
numbers and addition.
For example, you can prove
a plus b equals 2b plus a.
And this here is only
one file in Lean.
And if you are using Lean
to write formal mathematics,
it's similar to using Python
or another programming language
to develop software.
So you have one file and
this file has the proof,
and the proof is
it has semantics.
So you are starting-- it
corresponds to a proof tree.
At the root of this tree
is the original theorem
you want to prove.
And every step in this proof
decomposes the proof goal
into several simpler
subgoals, and you
can do that recursively until
all the subgoals are solved.
And this is one file, and files
are organized into larger units
like a project can
have many files.
And the project can be
open sourced on GitHub.
For example, in your project,
you can define real numbers.
And someone else's
project can build
on your definitions
of real numbers,
and they can formalize, for
example, optimization theory.
So this is similar to
how you develop software.
And one example of using
AI with Lean is AlphaProof.
That's the content
of the last lecture,
and it's a very
successful example.
And it uses Lean to
generate a lot of theorems
and a lot of proofs and
verify those proofs,
and do search and reinforcement
learning to learn the model.
So in the rest of
this lecture, we
will be talking about
mainly two tasks
at the center of
using Lean and AI.
So first is theorem proving.
In theorem proving, your
input is a theorem statement
and you want the model
to generate a proof.
Here, both the
statement and the proof
are written formally
in Lean, and the Lean
can check if the proof
is correct or not.
So there's no room for
the model to hallucinate.
And the other task is
auto formalization.
In autoformalization you have
the informal mathematics,
for example, from
a textbook, and you
want to use your
model to translate it
into formal mathematics.
So next we will be first
focusing on theorem proving.
And a very straightforward
way to do theorem proving
is you just give the model
what you want to prove,
and you ask the model to
generate a step in the proof
or you can ask it to
generate the entire proof.
And well, because if you
can generate the next step,
you can kind of using
search to chain steps
together into a complete proof.
So I would say,
the central problem
here is how do you
generate the next step?
And a very
straightforward solution
is, OK, we have human
written formal proofs.
And we can train a model
to do supervised learning
on those data so that
the model can learn
how to generate the next step.
And this idea has been
actually here for a while.
And earlier work used
classical machine
learning algorithms like
k nearest neighborhoods.
And around 2019,
people have started
to use deep neural
networks for this task.
And even later,
people are starting
to use large language models.
And I would say until the
use of large language models,
we really see a boost
in the performance
because the model can acquire
a lot of mathematical knowledge
during pre-training and use that
knowledge in theorem proving.
So we will be mainly talking
about this paper called
LeanDojo, which was
published in NeurIPS 2023.
So, well, in this paper we
provide open source data sets,
tools, and models for
theorem proving in Lean.
And compared to
previous approaches,
the main difference is first
we are completely open.
Previous approaches
are private and they
don't release the
data set and models
and they were done
in private labs.
And second, we
propose a new model
to generate the next
step in the proof.
So here is an overview.
So in Lean, we can extract data
from human written Lean code.
We extract about 10,000
theorems and proofs.
And for each proof, we have
the steps in the proof.
And we also have the
lemmas used in the proof
and also the definitions
of these lemmas.
And after extracting
this data set,
we use this data set to train
a machine learning model.
And once the model
is trained, the model
can interact with Lean
to prove new theorem.
And so here is the model we
introduced for this task.
It's called Retrieval-Augmented
Prover or ReProver.
The motivation is that
when you prove a theorem,
you almost never
start from scratch.
You use existing lemmas.
And in order to use
the existing lemmas,
the model have to know
what lemmas are there
and try to decide whether
a lemma is useful.
So here, given a
proof state, that's
the goal you want to prove.
And also given a library of
lemmas, so first do retrieval.
In this phase, we encode
everything into vectors.
So the state is now a vector
and each lemma becomes a vector.
And we compute the
similarity between the state
and each lemma, and
we use the result
to retrieve the top lemmas.
And after the lemmas
are retrieved,
we combine the
lemmas with the state
and use another language model
to generate the next step.
And so here, the
model is very simple,
but the really important point
is how do you get the data set?
And as we said in
LeanDojo you can
extract the data set from Lean.
From Lean projects like MathLib
and other Lean products.
So here is a summary of a
typical neural theorem prover.
So on the left, you see a tree.
So that's the tree
during proof search.
You have an initial
state and your model
can generate multiple
potential next steps.
And you can run those steps,
which gives you the next proof
state.
And you can do that repeatedly
until you find a proof.
So for this part, you can
use any search algorithm
like DFS or Monte
Carlo tree search.
And the second part is, how
do you generate the next step?
So on the right, you see at each
node in this proof search tree,
you have the current state.
So you give the current
state to the language model
and it generates
suggestions for you.
And here optionally,
the language model
can take a formal math library
which is the library of lemmas
you can use.
And so after the
LeanDojo work, we've
seen a bunch of work
trying to improve on that.
For example, one
thing you could do
is what we call
expert iteration.
So which is so
you have a prover.
Even if it's not
very good, you can
use it to attempt to
prove some new theorems.
And in this process, you
will get some new proofs.
And once you get
the new proofs, you
can add them into
your training set.
So now you have a
better training set,
and you can use
the better training
set to train a better prover.
And you can iterate.
So in this way, we show that
if you run for more iterations,
the performance usually improves
until you hit some saturation
point.
So we've seen a very
simple way to build
a theorem-proving model.
You just extract
human written proofs,
and you train a language model
to generate the next step
in the proof.
But we would say
it's a great step
but it comes with limitations.
So the first limitation
is still data.
Because language
models work well only
if you have a lot
of training data,
and the amount of human
written proofs on the internet
is very limited compared
to say Python code.
And also another limitation
is inherent to the task
of theorem proving.
So if you think
about other tasks
that AI has been
successful like playing Go.
So what's the difference
between playing Go
and proving a theorem?
The main difference is that in
Go you have a 19 by 19 board,
so the possible
action you can take
is constrained by the
size of the board.
It's finite.
But in mathematics,
arguably you can--
your action space is
infinite, so there
is infinite number of
things you could potentially
do when proving a theorem.
So since the action
space is infinite,
it's really hard to
cover the entire space
if you only learn from
human created data sets.
And even if you use
reinforcement learning,
it's very hard to explore
the space efficiently
during reinforcement learning.
That's a good question.
So in the work we
have talked up to now,
we are just using
supervised learning.
So there's no
curriculum involved.
But if you use
reinforcement learning,
it's natural to
have the model first
learn from relatively
simple examples
and then try to generalize.
And if you look at more recent
work in using reinforcement
learning for theorem
proving, one major difficulty
is how do you choose examples
to present to the model?
So you want the examples to be
not too easy, but also not too
hard.
So how do we solve the
limitation regarding the action
space?
So in a more recent
work we tried
to take a step in
that direction,
but we choose a very limited
domain as a playground.
So we prove inequalities
in Math Olympiad.
So inequalities in
Math Olympiad is
like you have a few
real numbers like ABC,
and they satisfy
some precondition.
And you want to prove a
postcondition like this.
And we choose this
domain because the proofs
in this domain is
highly regular.
So here is what humans would do.
Humans would do
typically two things.
One is you can apply an existing
lemma like AM-GM inequality
or Cauchy-Schwarz inequality.
And the other thing
people typically
do is to rewrite the
current formula into a form
so that an existing
lemma becomes applicable.
But even with these
two kind of actions,
the action space
is still very big.
For example, for proving
this particular inequality,
you can apply AM-GM.
And AM-GM can be applied
in more than one way,
so you have very big
branching factor.
And you can also
apply other inequality
like the T2 inequality,
and you can also
potentially choose to rewrite
the formula into this form.
So here the actions you can
take is essentially infinite.
So how do we navigate this
kind of infinite action space?
So one thing we do before trying
to solve the problem is, OK,
let's try to see how o1
can solve this problem.
And we give a lot of
inequality problems to o1
and we manually
check their proofs.
So as a result, we find a lot
of errors in the o1 produced
proofs.
And we checked 20 examples.
o1 preview proved none
of those examples.
And the more powerful o3
and also the DeepSeek-R1,
also only proved 3 or
4 out of 20 examples.
Whereas a typical gold medalist,
like a human gold medalist,
can prove at least 15.
So then let's come
to our method.
So as we said, we
categorize the steps
you can take in this particular
problem into two kinds.
First, we call it scaling.
Scaling is you apply
an existing lemma
like Cauchy-Schwarz to a
part of the current formula.
So in this example, you
find that the left part
of the formula can be
used for Cauchy-Schwarz
and which gives you the
result on the right hand side.
So what's special about scaling
is the number of scaling
you can do is finite.
This is because you only have
a finite number of lemmas,
and each lemma can be applied
in only a finite number of ways.
So it's actually
possible to enumerate
all the possible
scalings in this space.
And besides scaling, another
category is called rewriting.
Rewriting is you
are given a formula
and you want to transform
the current formula
into another form.
And rewriting is very different
from scaling in the sense
that the space is infinite.
So given any formula,
there are infinite number
of ways you can rewrite it.
So the key insight
here is that after we
make this categorization,
our algorithm
can enumerate all
the possible scalings
using a symbolic algorithm.
Whereas the rewriting,
selects the infinite space,
can be handled by
large language models.
So we combine the
next step generated
by the symbolic algorithm
with language models,
and we use some
heuristics to filter
the results to reduce
the number of goals
you have to improve search.
And as a result, we solved
a much more problems
compared to DeepSeek-R1
and also o3.
So here on the top you
see R1 proved 4 theorems.
Humans can prove 15,
whereas our system called
LIPS can prove 16 theorems.
And at the bottom, we evaluate
our system with a few benchmarks
and compare with
existing methods.
So here's one example,
one interesting example,
proof discovered by our system.
So here is interesting
because it's
from Evan Chen, who is IMO
coach for the Team USA.
And he has a problem set.
And he said, this problem has
no hope to be solved by AM-GM.
But we find that the proof
discovered by our system
uses only AM-GM combined
with clever rewriting.
So it can actually find
proofs that humans do not
know how to find.
So here is the takeaway.
The challenge in theorem proving
is how do you efficiently
explore a potentially
infinite action space?
And while this is a
very hard problem,
but if you are working on a
specific domain of mathematics,
you can use domain insight
to structure the action
space so that the action
space becomes more feasible.
But it is an open
problem of whether you
can generalize this approach
to be domain general.
So after talking
about theorem proving,
we will be going to
auto formalization.
And feel free to bring it
up any questions any time.
So in autoformalization,
we have informal math
and we have formal math.
And we want the model to be able
to build a bridge between them,
translating from
informal to formal.
And here, actually, we have two
slightly different subproblems.
First is how do we autoformalize
the theorem statement?
And second is, how do we
autoformalize the proofs?
In statement autoformalization,
the model only takes a statement
and produces the
statement in Lean.
But in proof
autoformalization, the model
have the informal statement,
the informal proof,
and also the formal
statement and it only
produces the formal proof.
So these two subproblems
have different challenges.
Let's talk about statement
formalization first.
For formalizing the
statement, it's really hard
to do the evaluation.
Because, for example, here
the informal statement says
there exists an infinite
number of primes.
And the formal statement says,
for any natural number n,
there exists a p that's
greater than or equal to n.
p is prime, so this is
obviously a correct translation
of the informal statement
because it implies the infinity.
But the problem is it's not
the only incorrect solution.
So if we produce
this solution, we
change p greater than or
equal to n to be strictly
greater than n, while
essentially it's the same.
And we can even make
it more different.
We can make n also a prime.
And for any human you can easily
see, OK, this three statements,
well, they are
slightly different,
but they are essentially
the same thing.
But this creates a problem
for machine learning.
So if the machine learning
model produces one of them.
How do you know if it's
equivalent to the ground truth?
You may want to say, OK, can I
check the logical equivalence?
But the reality is
this kind of checking
the equivalence
between two theorems
is computationally
infeasible, in general.
And in practice,
researchers have
resorted to heuristics
or human evaluation.
But if you rely on
human evaluation,
it's going to be very
expensive and not reproducible.
And if you resort to proxy
metrics or heuristics,
it's not going to be accurate.
So that's the challenge
for evaluating
the autoformalized statement.
How about proofs?
Proofs we have
another challenge.
Human written proofs are even
if they are very rigorous,
they are not rigorous
enough to be formalized.
They often have holes.
One kind of hole is like
mathematicians often
say, OK, this case is
left to the reader.
So if it's left to
the reader, your model
has no way to figure
it out from the text.
It has to figure it
out by their own.
And there are more subtle
holes in the proofs
that we will cover later.
But for the model to be able
to auto formalize the proof,
it kind of has to fill in
all those kind of gaps,
which can be very
difficult. So we've
covered two key challenges
in autoformalization.
For statement, we don't have a
reliable automatic evaluation.
And for proofs, the model has to
fill in all the reasoning gaps.
And in this project, we want
to address both problems.
So that sounds very intractable.
But a lesson we
learned in this project
is that since
intractable in general
can be made tractable
if you restrict
to a very specific domain.
And the domain we choose
is Euclidean geometry.
Euclidean geometry, it's
one of the oldest branches
of mathematics, and it has been
used to test human intelligence
for more than 2000 years.
And recently it has
become like of interest
by the AI community because of
the alpha geometry work, where
they have an AI that can
solve IMO low level geometry.
So in this work, we show that
Euclidean geometry is not only
a good domain for
theorem proving.
It's also a good domain
for formalization.
And more concretely, we collect
a benchmark called LeanEuclid
in Euclidean geometry.
It consists of 48 problems
from Euclid's Elements Book I
and more than 100
problems from UniGeo,
which is an existing data set.
So let's look at one
example in our data set.
So this is directly
from Euclid's Elements.
Its proposition one from
book I. It's basically you
have two points,
a and b, and you
want to show that it's
possible to construct
an equilateral triangle.
So for each problem,
you have the diagram
and the informal theorem
statement and also
the informal proof.
And when constructing
the benchmark,
we try to manually formalize
this problem in Lean.
So on the right hand side is
our formalization in Lean.
As you can see, it
corresponds very closely
to the informal version.
The first step is you draw a
circle BCD that's centered at A
and the B should
be on the circle.
And the second step is
you draw another circle,
and you try to find
the intersection
and you connect everything.
And then that's an
equilateral triangle.
So there are only 5 or 6
steps in the formal of proof,
and each step
corresponds perfectly
to what's being done
in the informal proof.
And we did this for
all the 48 theorems
and proofs in Euclid's
Elements, Book I.
And this is aesthetically
very pleasing for me,
because to the best
of our knowledge,
we are actually the
first to formalize
Euclid's Elements in a
proof assistants like Lean.
And while we want to keep
the proofs very faithful
in the sense that there
is a direct correspondence
between formal and informal.
And as we will see later,
this is not always trivial.
And during this process, we find
a few very interesting errors
in Euclid's Elements.
I think we can probably go
over one of those errors,
just to see how
formalization can
help you check mathematical
proofs rigorously and uncover
bugs in a proof
that you may think
it's already very rigorous.
So this is proposition
24 from Euclid's Book I.
It says if you
have two triangles,
and then the two
triangles have two pairs
of edges equal to each other.
So AC equals to DF and AB equals
to DE, so blue equals to blue,
red to equals to red.
And the angle A is
bigger than angle D.
So you want to show that
BC is greater than EF.
Well, this is doesn't
look very difficult,
and I'm going to show the
original proof by Euclid's.
So first you try to move
the triangle from the left
to overlap with the triangle on
the right, so C will become G.
And then you try
to connect F and G.
So now the problem becomes
proving EF greater than EG.
This is easier because EF and
EG are now in the same triangle.
And according to a previously
proved theorem in the same book,
in the same triangle,
a bigger angle
corresponds to a bigger edge.
So you only have to prove the
relationship between these two
angles.
You have to prove the big
angle here is indeed bigger
than the small angle, so how?
Just notice that we have
a isosceles triangle here.
We have DGF.
DG equals to DF.
And by our previously proved
lemma, in an isosceles angle--
in an isosceles
triangle, you have
two angles equal to each other.
So then you can
argue that the bigger
angle is bigger than
the DFG because it's
a superset of the BFG.
And the DFG is equal to DGF.
And the DGF is bigger
than the smaller angle.
Then you have proof
the bigger angle
is bigger than the small angle.
OK, so this is very trivial,
but the proof is actually wrong.
Anyone knows why?
No?
OK.
Well, technically it's not
wrong for this diagram,
but what if they look like this?
So let me try to
replay the proof.
First, move the triangle
from the left to the right.
Second, connect G
and F. Now, we want
to prove EF greater
than EG, and we
want to use this
isosceles triangles alpha.
So this alpha are equal.
And we want to prove x greater
than y using alpha, which
does not work directly.
Because in the previous
diagram, alpha is a part of x.
But now alpha is
outside x and y,
so you cannot use it as an
angle in the middle anymore.
So the original argument
break in this diagram.
So how do we fix this proof?
Well, luckily it's fixable.
Otherwise, we will probably
publish a bigger paper.
So first, notice that the
angle DGE, that's alpha plus y.
It's the inner
angle in a triangle,
so it's smaller than pi.
That's trivial.
And second, 2pi
minus alpha, minus x,
that's DFE is also
smaller than pi.
If you add these inequalities
together, alpha will cancel out
and you get x greater than y.
So it can be fixed, but as
you see this proof is quite
different from Euclid's proof.
So that's why we think Euclid's
has made an error here.
Or technically
it's not an error.
It's like this
proof has two cases.
These two cases are
slightly different
and the one case is more
challenging than the other.
But Euclid's omitted the
more challenging case
and focused on the easy case.
OK, maybe that's a very
interesting digression.
That's not related to AI,
but it showed how AI and Lean
can make things more rigorous.
So let's go back to AI.
So in our benchmark, the
first thing good about it
is it enables you to check
whether the autoformalized
theorem statement is correct.
So here is how we check if
the statement is correct.
We have a ground
truth, and we want
to check if it's logically-- if
the model-generated statement is
logically equivalent
to the ground truth.
So given two
theorems, T1 and T2,
we check it by proving
T1 implies T2 and T2 also
implies T1.
And here we use an
automated reasoning
tool called SMT solver.
But if you remember I said
that this is infeasible,
but how it becomes feasible now.
And it turns out
now it's feasible
because the theorems
in Euclidean geometry
takes a particular form.
They are not general theorems.
So problems
intractable in general
can be made tractable
in a specific domain.
And so that's how we check
the theorem statement.
Another problem is
autoformalizing the proofs.
So here in Euclidean geometry,
we want to show that--
we show that there
is a well known kind
of gaps in the proofs.
We call diagrammatic
reasoning gaps.
I'm going to show
that using an example.
So proposition one from
Euclid's Elements, Book I. Given
two points, A and
B, you can construct
a equilateral triangle.
Here is Euclid's proof.
Draw a circle centered at
A and B is on the circle.
Draw another circle centered
at B, A is on the circle.
Take the intersection, C,
and connect everything.
You get an equilateral triangle.
Anyone disagree with this proof?
No?
OK.
The problem is, did we
prove C actually exists?
Did we prove these two circles
actually have an intersection?
We didn't.
And actually if you try
to prove it, because--
so this is proposition one.
So to prove this proposition,
you can only use the axioms.
There's no existing lemmas.
And if you try to use Euclid's
axioms to try to prove these two
circles intersect, you
cannot prove it, actually.
So it's not provable.
But no one bothers to
prove it because it's just
so obvious in the diagram.
But it becomes a problem
if I want to translate
this proof in Lean.
When I formalize
the proof in Lean,
Lean does not know
what is the diagram
or what is obvious
in the diagram.
So I kind of have to formalize
what is obvious in the diagram.
I was in the Zoom
in the last lecture,
I believe someone
asked a question
about how do we formalize
Euclidean geometry in Lean.
I think this is very closely
related to that question.
To formalize Euclidean
geometry in Lean,
the most important thing, or
one of the most important thing,
is how do you formalize
the concept of being
obvious in the diagram?
And luckily, this problem has
actually been solved before.
So this is a work from Avigad
who is a professor in philosophy
now in CMU.
So Avigad essentially
identified a set
of axioms that's not in
Euclid's axiom system.
You can think of it as an
unspoken axiom or hidden axiom.
And so what is being
obvious in the diagram,
it is just if a fact is a
consequence of those axioms,
then it's obvious
in the diagram.
So now we have a
computational meaning
of obviousness in
the diagram, and we
can implement an automated
reasoning algorithm
to try to derive things
that are obvious.
So let me put
everything together.
So in this work, we
have a benchmark.
So in the benchmark
we have diagram.
We have informal
math and we have
a ground truth formal statement
that's written by human.
So now, we use a model
to do autoformalization.
It generates a formal
theorem, and we
can check whether it's
equivalent to the ground truth
using SMT solvers to prove
that they imply each other.
So after checking the
statement equivalence,
the model can also do
proof autoformalization.
Say it generates this proof
and we give this proof to Lean.
Lean will identify a set
of holes in the proof.
And we give those
holes to SMT solver,
which will tell us if the holes
are obvious in the diagram.
And if everything
works, then we conclude,
OK, this is a correct
formalization.
So what our benchmark
really do here
is we provide a
protocol that you
can use to rigorously
evaluate autoformalization.
And so after collecting
this benchmark,
we also did some very
simple experiments
using just GPT-4 and
the GPT-4 Vision.
And here we don't
train the model.
We just give a few
demonstrations to the model
and ask it to autoformalize
the theorem statement.
So blue here is
GPT-4 and green is
GPT-4 V, which also takes
the diagram as input.
And so here are two takeaways.
One is if you look at
the x-axis, is how many
demonstrations you
give to the model.
So if you give the model
more demonstrations,
it's going to do better.
But even if you give 5
demonstrations or even more,
the model get only about
20% which is pretty low,
which shows autoformalization
is very challenging.
And if you compare
green with blue,
you see green is a
little bit better.
Which shows if you give
the diagram to the model,
it has a stronger understanding
of the geometry problem.
And here are some takeaways.
We identified two challenges
in autoformalization.
For theorem statement, you
don't know how to evaluate.
For the proofs, there
are too many holes
in the human written proofs.
And we address them by
limiting to a specific domain.
So in this domain, we can
build a equivalence checker to
for the statement.
And we can build a tool that
can fill in all the gaps.
But still the open problem
is really how do you
generalize across a broader
set of mathematical domains?
So now we've covered both task,
autoformalization and theorem
proving.
And this is the end
of this lecture,
and I'm happy to take questions.